eeb2.eu 2019-03-03

# European School Privacy Statement – EEB2

                               Schola Europaea
                               Office of the Secretary-General
Ref.: 2018-06-D-21-en- 4
Orig.: EN
European School Privacy Statement – EEB2
                                                               1/6

                           European School Privacy Statement
                                      European School EEB2
Content
1.    What are the categories of personal data collected by the School? ............................. 3
2.    What are the purposes for which personal data are collected? .................................... 3
3.    What is the legal basis for the processing of personal data?........................................ 4
4.    Who has access to the personal data and whom do we share them with? ................... 4
5.    How do we protect and safeguard your information? ................................................... 5
6.    How long do we keep personal data? .......................................................................... 5
7.    What are your rights? .................................................................................................. 6
8.    Who should you contact in case of a complaint? ......................................................... 6
9.    Changes to this Privacy Statement .............................................................................. 6
The European Schools (hereinafter referred to as the ‘School’) are committed to respecting
your privacy and to complying with the requirements of Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the
European Parliament and of the Council of 27 April 2016, on the protection of natural
persons with regard to the processing of personal data and on the free movement of such
data (hereinafter, referred to as the ‘GDPR’).
‘Personal data’ means any information related to an identified or identifiable natural person.
In the School the ‘data subjects’ are in particular the pupils, and the legal
representatives/parents.
As defined by Article 4 (7) of the GDPR, the data ‘controller’ is the natural or legal person,
public authority, agency or other body which alone or jointly with others, determines the
purposes and means of the processing of personal data. As each European School has its
own legal personality1, the Director2 of each School is considered as a data ‘controller’.
This School Privacy Statement informs you about how the School processes the personal
data which are collected from legal representatives/parents and pupils. For instance, it sets
out what kind of personal data the School may collect, why it processes legal
representatives’/parents’ and pupils’ personal data and what your rights are in relation to
such data collection.
1 Article 6 of the Convention defining the Statute of the European Schools
2 Contact details: WOL-DIRECTOR@eursc.eu
2018-06-D-21-en-4                                                                                                         2/6

1.    What are the categories of personal data collected by the School?
The School and their employees will need to have access to and to process the following
personal data:
     a. Pupils
       Pupils’ first name(s), surname(s), home address, telephone numbers, passport
         details and other contact details,
       Pupils’ nationality, gender, languages spoken, country and town/city of birth,
       Pupils’ pedagogical information, linguistic competences, disciplinary information,
         references or information provided by previous educational establishments,
         attendance information (number of absences, reasons for absence),
       Pupils’ photo3,
     b. Legal representatives’ and parents
        Legal representatives’/parents’ contact details,
        Legal guardianship, parental custody, marital status, list of siblings,
        Legal representatives’/parents’ employment information,
        Legal representatives’/parents’ bank details and other financial information,
        Car details (only in the case of cars parking in the school grounds),
In addition, the School will need to process special categories of personal data, such as:
       Relevant information about pupils’ health.
2.    What are the purposes for which personal data are collected?
The European Schools are a sui generis intergovernmental organisation. Their purpose is
to provide children with quality teaching and learning, in the public interest.
To organise teaching and learning and in order to meet the pupils’ specific needs, the School
needs to process their personal data and those of the legal representatives/parents.
The School will use the personal data collected                           about    pupils   and     legal
representatives/parents for the following purposes:
        Enrolment of pupils.
        Organisation of timetables, classes, courses, including physical education and
         religion/ethics courses.
        Monitoring and reporting on pupils’ progress.
        Meeting educational needs, such as providing specific educational support.
        Pupils’ welfare, to provide appropriate medical care and to take appropriate action in
         the event of an emergency, including by disclosing details of an individual's medical
         condition where it is strictly in the individual's interests to do so (for example, to
         provide information to the organisers of schools trips or to doctors in case of an
         incident or accident).
        Communications with legal representatives/parents about pupils and about activities
         organised by the School.
        Transfer applications.
3   For the identification of the pupils by the School’s staff members. A consent form will be given to
    the legal representatives/parents for the use of pupils’ pictures for other purposes (taking pictures
    during school trips or school events).
2018-06-D-21-en-4                                                                                    3/6

        Determination of school fees
3.    What is the legal basis for the processing of personal data?
     a. Performance of a task carried out in the public interest
         As indicated above, the purpose of the European Schools is to provide children with
         quality teaching and learning, in the public interest.
         Therefore, the processing of the collected personal data (as stated in section 1), is
         necessary for the performance of a task carried out in the public interest, pursuant to
         the Convention defining the Statute of the European Schools, the General Rules of
         the European Schools and the Regulations for the European Baccalaureate
         (available for consultation on the European Schools’ website).
     b. Explicit consent/Provision of health or social care
         Where processing of special categories of personal data, such as pupils’ health
         information, is necessary, a consent will be requested from the legal
         representatives/parents.
         The processing of pupils’ health information by the psychologist or the nurses of the
         School can also be necessary for the provision of health or social care.
     c. Compliance with a legal obligation
         Where processing is necessary to comply with a legal obligation to which the School
         is subject, information will be shared with National Authorities.
4.    Who has access to the personal data and whom do we share them with?
     a. Access to the personal data
         Personal data collected by the School will be processed within the School.
         To facilitate the management of the School’s activities, the staff members will use
         some service providers’ software and IT solutions (i.e: SMS, O365, SAP).
         Contractual agreements are in place to ensure that these service providers are fully
         compliant with the GDPR’s provisions and act only in accordance with the School’s
         specific directions.
         Data processing activities will be handled only by staff members with a legitimate
         need to access the pupils and legal representatives/parents’ personal data, for the
         purposes described above.
         In particular, strict access rules apply to the following personal data:
         -        Health information is collected and accessed only by the School Doctor and
                  Nurses, the School Psychologist and other specially authorised staff, to
                  ensure pupils’ welfare.
         -        Relevant health information provided by legal representatives/parents to the
                  coordinators of a school trip will be kept only for the duration of the trip in
                  question and will be destroyed afterwards.
         -        Information relating to the option chosen for religion/non-confessional ethics
                  courses will be used only for the organisation of such courses.
2018-06-D-21-en-4                                                                            4/6

          All the staff members of the School are committed to protecting the confidentiality
          of your personal information in the performance of their tasks. They also received
          data protection training in order to act in accordance with the GDPR’s provisions.
     b. Data sharing
            i.    Security Guards
            To ensure security and access to the School, the security guards of the School
            will be provided with the relevant information.
           ii.    Central Enrolment Authority
            In Brussels, enrolment applications are handled by the Central Enrolment
            Authority (CEA) at the Office of the Secretary-General of the European Schools,
            pursuant to the provisions of the Policy on Enrolment in the Brussels European
            Schools for the current school year (available for consultation on the European
            Schools’ website: https://www.eursc.eu).
            The School will share the relevant information with the CEA in order to award a
            place at one of the Brussels Schools/Sites.
            The School to which the application is submitted will keep the enrolment
            application only if the pupil is ultimately enrolled in this School. If the pupil is not
            enrolled in the School corresponding to the first preference, the enrolment
            application will be sent to the School where the place is awarded.
            The CEA will keep an electronic and hard copy (paper) version of enrolment
            information for administrative purposes for ten years.
5.    How do we protect and safeguard your information?
In order to protect pupils’ and legal representatives’/parents’ personal data, a number of
technical and organisational measures have been put in place. These include appropriate
measures to address online security, physical security, risk of data loss, alteration or
unauthorised access, taking into consideration the risk represented by the processing and
the nature of the data being protected.
In addition, we restrict access to the databases containing personal data to authorised
persons with a legitimate need to access such information, for the purposes described
above.
6.    How long do we keep personal data?
We will keep personal data for as long as the pupils are enrolled in our School. Information
relating to disciplinary measures will be erased from the file three years after the point in
time when the measure was imposed.
When pupils have completed their education in our School, we will keep individual files for
ten years. A duplicate copy of the Baccalaureate diploma, certificates of achievement and
school attendance certificates will be kept for archiving purposes, in the public interest.
2018-06-D-21-en-4                                                                               5/6

7.    What are your rights?
With respect to the processing of your personal data, you have the right to be informed and
to access your personal data. You also have the right to rectification, erasure and to object
to the processing.
Where the School processes personal data on the basis of consent, such consent may be
withdrawn at any time.
To facilitate the exercise of your rights, you may submit your request to our Data Protection
Officer Correspondent: WOL-DPO-CORRESPONDENT@eursc.eu
The School will respond to these requests without undue delay and within one month at the
latest. Should the School decline to comply with a request, you will be informed of the
reasons for such a decision.
8.    Who should you contact in case of a complaint?
If you consider that the School has not complied with the data protection laws applicable
(including the GDPR) or that your rights have been infringed as the result of the processing
of your personal data, you have the right of recourse and can contact the National
Supervisory Data Protection Authority.
9.    Changes to this Privacy Statement
We reserve the right to update this Privacy Statement at any time, and we will provide you
with a new Privacy Statement when we make substantial changes.
2018-06-D-21-en-4                                                                        6/6
